Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is ק. kuf. We
are in the triple digits if you're counting in Arabic numerals. מנחות
Menachos 100, and we pick up with the משנה, Mishnah, still talking
about the לחם הפנים. Lechem HaPanim. סידור הלחם בשבת והבזיכין לאחר שבת.
Sideur halechem beshabbos v'habezichin l'achar shabbos. So it's about a third of
the way down on ק עמוד א. kuf amud aleph. סידור הלחם
בשבת והבזיכין לאחר שבת, Sideur halechem beshabbos v'habezichin l'achar shabbos, if the
כהנים Kohanim somehow messed up and they only and they put the
bread on the table on שבת Shabbos but they only put the
incense, the frankincense on it on Sunday.
והקטיר הבזיכין בשבת Vehiktir habezichin beshabbos and then they offered it up,
you know on the following שבת, Shabbos, the normal time to offer
it up, but it had only been on the שולחן Shulchan for
six days the the frankincense, not for the week, פסול pasul it
is invalid, okay. As רש"י Rashi says, if you look at רש"י:
Rashi: דמחוסר זמן הוא שלא היה על השולחן אלא ששי ימים, demichusar
zman hu shelo haya al hashulchan ela shishi yamim, okay, that it
is not yet considered its time to be offered up. It is
understood that a prerequisite for it to be offered is that it
has been on the שולחן Shulchan for the full seven days. And
therefore if you did offer it up, you did not make the
bread fit to be eaten because it did not have the מתיר
matir which is the frankincense was not offered up properly. And therefore
אין חייבין עליהם משום פיגול נותר וטמא. ein chayavin aleihem mishum pigul
notar vetamei. If you had a thought of פיגול, pigul, the bread
does not become פיגול pigul when you offered it up, again because
it's not, the מתיר matir has not been offered correctly. If it
is left over and you eat from it the next day, it's
not נותר notar because it has never become permissible to be eaten
the bread. And similarly if a טמא tamei person ate it, he
does not get כרת kares because he only gets כרת kares if
a טמא tamei person eats something that was fit to be eaten
and this bread was never fit to be
eaten. Okay, and fine. And the סידור sidur now actually I should
say, so the question would be, well why not just offer up
the בזיכין bezichin on Sundays so it will be there for all
seven days? But the answer is the בזיכין bezichin can only be
left offered up on שבת. Shabbos. And besides which as רש"י Rashi
says, because the bread was put up on the right time on
שבת, Shabbos, so the bread will no longer be valid when it
gets to be Sunday. The bread is only going to be valid
if the בזיכין bezichin were offered up a week, you know, from
when the bread was put on the table. So you have no
solution there. Alright, now סידור הלחם והבזיכין בשבת. sidur halechem v'habezichin beshabbos.
They were both put up properly on שבת. Shabbos. והקטיר הבזיכין לאחר
השבת. Vehiktir habezichin l'achar hashabbos. And then you were late in offering
up the בזיכין. bezichin. So again you are not offering up the
מתיר כמצותו. matir kemitzvaso. So
לאחר השבת פסולה, l'achar hashabbos psula, so it is invalid, the מתיר
matir was not offered up
properly. ואין חייבין עליהם משום פיגול נותר וטמא, ve'ein chayavin aleihem mishum
pigul notar vetamei, the same reason that the those things are only
relevant if you know the פיגול pigul if the מתיר matir was
offered כמצותו, kemitzvaso, נותר וטמא notar vetamei if the bread became permissible
to be eaten, which it did not because the לבונה levona was
not offered up on
שבת. Shabbos. סידור הלחם והבזיכין לאחר השבת. Sidur halechem v'habezichin l'achar hashabbos.
Let's say you missed all of שבת Shabbos and everything was put
up on Sunday.
והקטיר הבזיכין בשבת, Vehiktir habezichin beshabbos, and then you offered them up
on the following שבת, Shabbos, פסולה psula again, once again it is
invalid because it has not been a full week. But here we
have a solution. כיצד יעשה? Keitzad yaaseh? What should you do? יניחנה
לשבת הבאה. Yani'chena lashabbos haba'ah. Leave the bread on the table until
the next שבת. Shabbos. How's that going to work? שאפילו היא על
השולחן ימים רבים אין בכך כך. She'afilu hi al hashulchan yamim rabim
ein bechach kach. Even if it's on the שולחן Shulchan for a
very long time, it is no problem. Now it doesn't mean that
in an absolute sense. What it means is that because it was
put up on Sunday, it was never the clock didn't start ticking.
It was not put up in the right time, okay? So since
so the שולחן Shulchan was never מקדש mekadesh it and the clock
you and the clock didn't start ticking. And the clock only starts
ticking six days later and then, you know, when next שבת, Shabbos,
then it's considered oh, the שולחן Shulchan is here on a שבת,
Shabbos, שבת Shabbos late but it's here on a שבת, Shabbos, then
the then it's becomes sanctified and then the clock starts ticking and
then you can offer up the בזיכין bezichin the following שבת, Shabbos,
okay? So it's not just leaving it doesn't matter, right? Because if
that were true, then it would be a solution to one of
the previous cases, right? Let's say you put the what do you
know, if you put the bread up on שבת Shabbos and the
בזיכין bezichin on Sunday, so why not just leave the bread for
two weeks and then offer the בזיכין bezichin after you know six
days and a week. And the answer is no, that you can't
do because when the bread is put up on שבת Shabbos the
clock starts ticking. But here everything was put up after שבת, Shabbos,
so the clock did not start ticking until the next שבת Shabbos
and therefore you can offer it thirteen days later. Okay, תנן, tnan,
we תנן התם. tnan hasam. We taught over there in תמיד. Tamid.
אמר להם הממונה, Amar lahem hamemuneh, צאו וראו אם הגיע זמן שחיטה.
tze'u ur'u im higiya zman shechita. So
you know this is in יומא Yoma also, they wanted to make
sure that it was time to שחט shecht the קרבנות korbanos in
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. אם, im, you know if the day
had become light and then they could bring
שחט shecht the
תמיד. tamid. אם הגיע רואה אם
הגיע Im higia ro'eh im higia if the time came,
the one who saw it said ברקאי Barkai like you know, but
it's like it's almost like an onomatopoeia, like sort of like the
day is lit. Okay, ברק Barak is like a lightning. מתיא בן
שמואל אומר האיר
פני כל המזרח עד שבחברון Mattia ben Shmuel omer he'ir pnei kol
hamizrach ad shebeChevron so מתיא בן שמואל Mattia ben Shmuel said that
now you know it now if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י
Rashi says he himself was the ממונה, memuneh, so what he would
use to say when he was doing this job is he would
he would ask the person האיר פני כל המזרח עד שבחברון? He'ir
pnei kol hamizrach ad shebeChevron? Has the whole east gotten light that
you can even see you know light light light over in חברון?
Chevron? והוא אומר הן Vehu omer hen and he would say yes.
Okay, so he wouldn't just take him quickly when he said oh
it's light, he would double check that you know make sure that
it was clearly day. ולמה הוצרכו לכך? Velama hutzrechu lekach? Why was
that necessary? שפעם אחת עלה מאור הלבנה Shepa'am achat ala me'or halevana
one day they it was you know the the the moonlight had
come up come up you know the moon rises at different times,
ודימו שהאיר מזרח Vedimu shehe'ir mizrach and they thought that it was
the sunrise and it was the east, שחטו את התמיד Shachtu es
hatamid they slaughtered the תמיד Tamid והוציאוהו לבית השריפה Vehotzi'uhu leveit hasreifah
and they had to go ahead and burn it because it was
slaughtered while it was still night. והורידו כהן גדול לבית הטבילה Vehoridu
kohen gadol leveit hatvilah and they had to bring the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol to the
בית הטבילה Beit Hatvilah that's a whole discussion what that's about, not
for our issue. זה הכלל היה במקדש Ze haklal haya baMikdash this
was
right because like why is this specifically talking about the כהן גדול?
Kohen Gadol? So that's you know probably more likely in a יום
כיפור Yom Kippur context. But the point is like this, now that
it is daylight and that you are offering the תמיד, Tamid, okay,
so והורידו כהן גדול לבית הטבילה Vehoridu kohen gadol leveit hatvilah it
was time for the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol to go to the
מקוה. mikvah. זה הכלל היה במקדש Ze haklal haya baMikdash this was
the general rule in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. כל המסך את
רגליו Kol hameseach es raglav anybody this is a euphemism who basically
would defecate טעון טבילה ta'un tvila
would have to go to the מקוה. mikvah. וכל המטיל מים Vechol
hametil mayim and anybody who would urinate טעון קידוש ידים ורגלים ta'un
kidush yadayim veraglayim would wash their hands and feet. Okay, so that
was you know not strictly required but that was how they would
do the standard practice in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. תני אבוה
דרבי
אבין Tani avuh deRabbi Abin because טבילה tvila specifically for being טמא,
tamei, defecating is not about that you know but anyway that's what
they would do because obviously it's a way of showing preparing yourself
for the עבודה avoda in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. תני אבוה
דרבי אבין Tani avuh deRabbi Abin taught לא זו בלבד אלא אפילו
עולת העוף שנמלקה בלילה ומנחה שנקמצה בלילה תצא לבית השריפה. Lo zo
bilvad ela afilu olas ha'of shenimleka balaila umincha shenikmitza balaila taitzei leveit
hasreifah.
Okay, so this is what we're going to focus on and we'll
see how this is going to be relevant to our משנה, mishnah,
right why are we talking about this at all? So we'll see
the conversation will turn back to our משנה. mishnah. But he said
we're not only talking with they slaughtered a בהמה, behema, a cow
or a sheep or a goat you know before while it was
still night that it would have to be burnt and it was
not valid, but even if it was a bird and even if
it was a מנחה. mincha. Okay, everything is invalid at night. So
we'll see what the חידוש chiddush is. בשלמא Bishlama says the גמרא
Gemara says I get עולת העוף olas ha'of משום דלא אפשר לאהדורה.
mishum delo efshar lehahadura. Okay,
a bird I get it you know you can't make the bird
back alive. And if the עבודה avoda is not כשר kosher until
it's day, that's true about the bird as well. אלא מנחה אפשר
דמהדר לה לדוכתא וקמיץ ביממא. Ela mincha efshar demahadar lah leduchta vekamitz
biyemama.
But a מנחה mincha fine I get that taking the קומץ komets
wasn't valid, but why not just put it back into the original
vessel and do it again? Good question and do it again when
it's daytime. הוא תני לה והוא אמר לה Hu tani lah vehu
amar lah he taught it and he explained it, explicated, כלי שרת
מקדשין שלא בזמנם. Klei sharet mekadeshin shelo bizmanam. Because when you put
the קומץ komets into a כלי שרת, kli sharet, right and that
makes the קומץ komets now fit to be offered up on the
מזבח, mizbe'ach, so that works even at night. Okay, you could have
said if it's not yet the time for it the כלי שרת
kli sharet didn't raise it to that level and make it designated
like as a קומץ komets and unable to be put back. And
his חידוש chiddush is no, even שלא בזמנם, shelo bizmanam, you know
it actually sanctifies it, designates it and now it cannot be put
back into the
מנחה. mincha. מיתיבי Meitivei this is going to be our focus, this
claim. Okay, מיתיבי Meitivei I'll challenge you on that כל הקרב ביום
קדוש ביום Kol hakarev bayom kadosh bayom so here we have a
teaching in תמורה Temurah anything that was offered in the day you
know is sanctified in the day. בלילה קדוש בלילה Balaila kadosh balaila
if it's for nighttime it's sanctified at the nighttime. בין ביום ובין
בלילה Bein bayom uvein balaila if it can be done day or
night. Okay, so by the way what are these? So something in
the day is a normal קרבן. korban. So if you put it
so it seems to be saying the כלי שרת, kli sharet, this
is the simple how the גמרא's Gemara understanding it, operates at the
time when the קרבן korban is good. So for a normal קרבן
korban a day something in the day, the כלי שרת kli sharet
operates in the day. Something Something that's night, okay, which is, you
know, like for example, I mean it could—it's valid at night, you
know רש״י *Rashi* says כגון מנחת נסכים nesachim, *kegon minchat nesachim*, okay?
You can—it's valid if you offered them at night, if you offered
the קרבן korban, *korban* in the day. So the כלי שרת kli
shares *kli sharet* will work in the day. קדש בין ביום ובין
בלילה *kadesh bein bayom
ubein balaila*, it could be day or night, which is also, you
know, the מנחת נסכים nesachim *minchat nesachim*, hard to figure out what
exactly is the thing that's only day, only night, קדש בין ביום
ובין בלילה *kadesh bein bayom ubein balaila*. Okay so that now is—so
okay so that seems to be exactly this. The כלי שרת kli
shares *kli sharet* works if it's put in it at the time
when the קרבן korban *korban* can be offered. So כל הקרב ביום
קדש ביום, ביום אין, בלילה לא *kol hakarev bayom kadesh bayom, bayom
in, balaila lo*. So look, it's very clear. If it's a day
thing, it's sanctified in the day, day yes, not night. So if
you tried to put it in a כלי שרת kli shares *kli
sharet*, it would not operate at night. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s
pretty clear. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no. אינו קדוש kadosh
ליקרב אבל קדוש kadosh ליפסל *eino kadosh l'hikarev aval kadosh l'hipasel*. Okay
so it's like the worst of both worlds. Because it was in
the כלי שרת kli shares *kli sharet*, it's enough to give it
its identity as a מנחה mincha *mincha*, as a קומץ komets. *komets*,
but because it was at the wrong time, it's not fit to
be offered up, okay? It was done at the wrong time, but
it was close enough and it was in a כלי שרת kli
shares *kli sharet* that it was a מנחה mincha, *mincha* that it
was a קומץ *komets*. So it's like a קומץ פסולה *komets psula*.
It's the worst of both because it was the wrong time, it's
פסול posul. *pasul*, because it was a כלי שרת kli shares, *kli
sharet*, it's still a קומץ *komets*. קדוש ליפסל *kadosh l'hipasel*. Okay. So
מוסיף
רבי זירא *mosif Rabbi Zeira*, Rabbi Zeira challenged this. סידור הלחם ואת
הבזיכין *siddur halechem ve'et habazichin*—now we're going to see why we're discussing
this in our context. Okay. סידר את הלחם ואת הבזיכין אחר שבת
Shabbos. *sidar es halechem ve'es habazichin achar Shabbos*, if you put the
bread and the בזיכין *bazichin* with the לבונה levona *levona*, frankincense on
the table on Sunday, this is the one case in the Mishnah
that worked, okay? אחר שבת Shabbos והקטיר הבזיכין בשבת *achar Shabbos vehiktir
habazichin be-Shabbos*, and you offered it up on the Shabbos itself, okay,
פסולה *psula*, it's invalid because that's only six days. כיצד Keitzad? יעשה
*keitzad ya'aseh*, so what can you do? יניחנו לשבת הבאה *yanichenu l'Shabbos
haba'ah*, you wait till the next Shabbos, שאפילו היה השולחן ימים רבים
*she'afillu haya hashulchan yamim rabim*, even if it's been sitting on the
table for six days until it gets to, you know, the Shabbos,
until it gets to a Shabbos and total 13 days, אין בכך
כלום *ein bekach klum*, it's not a problem. And the way we
explained this in the Mishnah, you'll remember, is that since those six
days it was not fit to be on the שולחן Shulchan. *shulchan*,
it's only fit to be on the שולחן Shulchan. *shulchan* if it's
put up on Shabbos, so the clock didn't start ticking until it
hit the next Shabbos. And then the clock started ticking and then
the Shabbos after that, you know, total 13 days, seven days after
it hit the first Shabbos, that's when now you're going to offer
it up. So that only works and the bread and the בזיכין
*bazichin* don't become invalid because the clock didn't start ticking because you
put them up not on Shabbos, meaning שלא בזמנם *shelo bizmanom*, you
put them up at the wrong time. So, and ואי סלקא דעתך
*ve'i salka daitach* כלי שרת kli shares מקדש שלא בזמנו mekadesh shelo
bizmano. *kli sharet mekadesh shelo bizmano*, and if you think a כלי
שרת kli shares *kli sharet* works שלא בזמנו bizmano. *shelo bizmano*, minimally
at least to invalidate something, right? Maybe not to make it fit
to be offered, but to invalidate it, ליקדש וליפסול *likadesh ve-lifsul*, this
should be just like, you know, the קומץ *komets* of the מנחה
mincha *mincha*. It was the wrong time but it got designated as
a קומץ *komets* and now it can't be used. So let this
bread be designated as לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim, *lechem hapanim* and now
it can't be used because it's now, you know, פסול posul. *pasul*
after seven
days. And seven days is Sunday, right? It can't—Shabbos is too soon
and the next Shabbos is too late. Good question. So, okay. So
אמר רבא: Amar Rava
מאן דקמוסיף
שפיר קמוסיף *amar Rava: man dekamosif shapir kamosif*. The one who asked
the question, that was a good question, that טאקע *taka* is a
very good question. By the time you hit day eight, it should
be considered to be, you know, beyond its time. Let the clock
start ticking even שלא בזמנו bizmano. *shelo bizmano*. אבוה דרבי אבין נמי
מתניתא קאמר *avuha d'Rabbi Avin nami masnisa ka'amar*. Oh, excuse me, I
read that wrong. Oh no, I take it back, I did read
it right. Okay. So I thought for some second it was rhetorical.
But he says, no, the question is a good question and despite
the fact that the question is a good question, מאן דקמוסיף שפיר
קמוסיף *man dekamosif shapir kamosif*, but nevertheless אבוה דרבי אבין נמי מתניתא
קאמר *avuha d'Rabbi Avin nami masnisa ka'amar*. The father of Rabbi Avin
was also quoting a ברייתא braita: *braita*. Right, Rabbi Avin—the father of
Rabbi Avin wasn't making it up. He had a ברייתא *braita* that
actually said that a מנחה mincha *mincha* done at night is invalid
and can't be rectified. So that ברייתא *braita* definitely seems—only makes sense
if the כלי שרת kli shares *kli sharet* works שלא בזמנו bizmano
*shelo bizmano*. So how do you fit that in together with our
Mishnah about the bread, which seems to be that the clock doesn't
start ticking שלא בזמנו bizmano *shelo bizmano*? So what's the resolution? קסבר
לילה אין מחוסר זמן, mechusar zeman. הימים מחוסרין זמן *kasavar laila ein
mechusar zman, hayamim mechusarin zman*. So here's the way that you can
make both of them work. Night, right, if you do the מנחה
mincha *mincha* right before daybreak, since it's like the night leading into
the following day, it's considered to be close enough. is enough that
it's not considered to be lacking in time. Again, it's invalid because
it was done at night, but because this is the day of
that you of being מקריב the קרבן, korban, then when you did
it in the nighttime of that day, right, it is not like
you did it at the totally wrong time and the כלי שרת
Klei Shares? is meaningless. Okay, so the night of the day in
which it can be brought is considered to be enough בזמנו. bizmano,
It's invalid because it was done at night, but it's בזמנו.
הימים מחוסרים זמן. Hayamim mechusrim zeman. But you know the days, meaning,
if you do it six days before with the לחם הפנים, that
is completely the wrong time and therefore the clock does not start
ticking. So in this explanation conceptually כלי שרת Klei Shares, is only
מקדש בזמנו. mekadesh bizmano. It's not מקדש שלא בזמנו. mekadesh shelo bizmano,
It doesn't start with the bread. Okay, that's why the bread the
clock doesn't start ticking on a Sunday six days before. It's not
מקדש mekadesh שלא בזמנו, but it works in the מנחה mincha done
at night to make it invalid because night isn't considered מחוסר זמן.
mechusar zeman, Night is close enough. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara
though has a problem. The גמרא Gemara, says הימים מחוסרים זמן. hayamim
mechusarim zeman. So סוף סוף sof sof says the גמרא Gemara. okay,
but in the final analysis top of ק' עמוד עמוד ב', Kuf
Amud Amud Bes, כי מטו לילה דבי שמשי לקדש וליפסול? ki matu
laila d'bei shimshi likadesh v'lifsol? This is a good question. Okay, fine,
night isn't מחוסר זמן, mechusar zeman, but when it becomes the night
of like after the six days have passed and now it is
ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, not ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, now it's like
Friday night, okay, so it was put up on Sunday, six days
passed, it's Friday night. So now it is the night before you
would put the bread on the table. So since it is the
night before you would put the bread on the table, that's not
considered מחוסר זמן, mechusar zeman, this bread has been on the table
for six days, it did not get sanctified because that was מחוסר
זמן, it was way too soon. But now the night before is
not considered way too soon, so that should sanctify it, that should
get the clock ticking sooner and that should invalidate it by the
time you get, you know, to the next שבת. Shabbos, So why
doesn't that happen? Why didn't the night before, the Friday night, start
the clock ticking and create problems? לקדש וליפסול. Likadesh v'lifsol. So אמר
רבא בשקדמו וסילקו. beshekodmo v'seelayko. Okay,
so what you did was that when it was, you know, it
was on the table since Sunday and then before and through Friday,
and before Friday night you took it off the table, then you
kept it I don't know in one of those tables in the
אולם, Ulam, and then שבת Shabbos morning you put it back on
the שולחן. Shulchan, So you actually took it off the כלי שרת
Klei Shares? when it was the night before because you don't want
to get the clock starting ticking. That's a nice answer. מר זוטרא
ואיתימא רב אשי אמר Mar Zutra v'isayma Rav Ashi amar אפילו תימא
בשלא קדמו וסילקו, afilu tayma beshelo kodmo v'seelayko, even if you didn't
do that, כיון דסידורו שלא כמצוותו נעשה כמי שסידרו הקוף. keivan desiduro
shelo kemitzvato naaseh kemi shesidro hakof.
Since it was put up so much before, six days before, it's
not just שלא כמצוותו, shelo kemitzvato, but like such a time before,
not just the night before, so it's like it wasn't even an
act of being placed on the שולחן. It was like a monkey
did it. Okay, it was almost like, you know, it was completely
irrelevant how it got on the שולחן, it was so earlier before.
So by the time you come along and it's now Friday night,
it's just like the bread was like there without an act of
being placed there. And in that context, it's not מקדש it. It
needs to have a meaningful act. What he's basically saying is in
the case of the מנחה, mincha, you did the act the night
before. It was enough, not only was it considered enough בזמנו for
the כלי, kli, it was enough בזמנו for the act of taking
the קומץ. So it was close enough to be meaningful and therefore
was פסול. Okay, you the כלי שרת Klei Shares. operated, it was
considered בזמנו, it was פסול. But that's because the act was meaningful
as well because the act was the night before as well. But
when the act is so much earlier, every its whole placement here
is seen as random and not meaningful and the כלי שרת Klei
Shares, doesn't operate at all. Alrighty, that was very interesting in terms
of כלי שרת שלא בזמנו. kli shares shelo bizmano. Last משנה mishnah
of the פרק. perek.
שתי הלחם נאכלות אין פחות משנים ולא יותר על שלשה. Shtei HaLechem
ne'echalos ein pachos mishnayim v'lo yoser al shlosha. So the שתי הלחם
Shtei HaLechem of שבועות Shavuos is not eaten no fewer than two
days from the time counting the day they were cooked and the
day it was eaten, baked, and no more than three. כיצד? How
does this work? נאפות מערב יום טוב נאכלות ביום טוב. Ne'efos me'erev
Yom Tov ne'echalos b'Yom Tov. Since its baking is not דוחה יום
טוב. docheh Yom Tov. Now you might ask why not? It's like
if you can bake bread at home for יום טוב, Yom Tov,
right, it's אוכל נפש ochel nefesh is permissible, you can do it
also maybe for the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem that's going to be
eaten by the כהנים, Kohanim, so we'll see about that in a
minute. But the assumption is is that it's not דוחה יום טוב.
docheh Yom Tov. And therefore, and it doesn't, you know, you don't
put it in the it doesn't get sanctified for there to be
a problem of לינה lina for the clock to start ticking, you
know, by the time it's baked, that doesn't start it, it's when
the קרבן korban, is שחט shechted for the שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem.
לחם *lechem*, so therefore you bake it the day before יום טוב
Yom Tov *Yom Tov* and you and it and you eat it
on יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov* that is on day two.
Okay, לשני *leshanei*, that's day two. חל יום טוב Yom Tov, להיות
אחר השבת *chal Yom Tov liyot achar HaShabbos*, if יום טוב Yom
Tov. *Yom Tov* is Sunday, so we already decided for whatever reason
you can't bake it on יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*, you
can't bake it on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*, so you're gonna bake it
on Friday. So נאכלות לשלושה *ne'echalos lishlosha*, it's eaten after three days:
Friday, שבת *Shabbos*, Sunday. All right, לחם הפנים *Lechem HaPanim* and all
of these, like both לחם הפנים *Lechem HaPanim* and the שתי הלחם
shtei halechem *shtei halechem*, the clock doesn't start ticking you know right
away you know by the שתי הלחם shtei halechem? *shtei halechem* only
when the קרבן korban. *korban* is שחט shacht *shechted*, by the לחם
הפנים *Lechem HaPanim* you know when you get seven days from the
time it's put on on שבת *Shabbos*. Okay, but the clock only
starts ticking when it's put on the שולחן *shulchan*. לחם הפנים *Lechem
HaPanim* נאכל *ne'echal* and then when is so לחם הפנים *Lechem HaPanim*
when is that eaten? אין פחות מתשעה *ein pachus mitish'ah*, no fewer
than nine days from the day it's baked, ולא יותר על אחד
עשר *velo yoter al echad asar*, no more than 11. כיצד *keitzad*,
how does this work? נאפה מערב שבת *ne'efa me'erev Shabbos*, if it
was baked, again its baking isn't דוחה שבת *doche Shabbos* as we
said, because even though it has to be brought on שבת *Shabbos*
it doesn't have to be baked on שבת *Shabbos*. So you bake
it on Friday, ונאכל בשבת לתשעה *vene'echal beShabbos letish'ah*, and then you
eat it the following שבת *Shabbos*. So that is nine days if
you count the day that it was baked and the day that
it was eaten. חל יום טוב Yom Tov, להיות ערב שבת *chal
Yom Tov liyot erev Shabbos*, if יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*
is on Friday, so you don't bake it on יום טוב Yom
Tov *Yom Tov* if you can't bake the שתי הלחם shtei halechem
*shtei halechem* on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* to eat it
on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*, you can't bake the לחם
הפנים *Lechem HaPanim* on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* to eat
it a שבת *Shabbos* eight days from now. Okay, חל יום טוב
Yom Tov להיות ערב שבת נאכל לעשרה *chal Yom Tov liyot erev
Shabbos ne'echal l'asarah*, it's eaten after 10 days, right? So if it's
so you can't bake it on Friday which is יום טוב *Yom
Tov*, so you bake it on Thursday, so Thursday, Friday, שבת *Shabbos*,
Sunday, Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday, Friday, שבת *Shabbos*, that's that is 10
days. שני ימים טובים של ראש השנה *shenei yamim tovim shel Rosh
Hashanah*, if if ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah* is Thursday, Friday,
so then נאכל לאחד עשר *ne'echal l'echad asar*, it's eaten at 11,
'cause you don't do it on either day יום טוב *Yom Tov*,
so you'd start on Wednesday, Wednesday till the next שבת *Shabbos* is
11 days. All right, now רש״י *Rashi* says, ah, you're gonna ask
that if ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah* is Thursday, Friday, then שבת *Shabbos*
is day three of תשרי *Tishrei* and next שבת *Shabbos* is יום
כיפור *Yom Kippur*, so how can you eat it next שבת *Shabbos*?
So רש״י *Rashi* says you eat it at night, you know you
eat it מוצאי שבת *motzaei Shabbos* and that is so you're still
eating it within the 11 days because the bread doesn't become פסול
*pasul* until the Sunday morning. All right, תוספות *Tosafot* actually says it's
not a question because at the time of the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash* when they had two days of ראש השנה *Rosh
Hashanah*, it actually was as opposed to us where day one is
number one of תשרי *Tishrei*, in the time of the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash* it would be two days of ראש השנה
*Rosh Hashanah*, the second day of ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah* would be
day one of תשרי *Tishrei*. So whole other discussion. Fine. ואינו דוחה
לא את השבת ולא את יום טוב *ve'eino doche lo es HaShabbos
velo es Yom Tov*, which says what's implicit, baking the שתי הלחם
shtei halechem *shtei halechem*, לחם הפנים *Lechem HaPanim* isn't דוחה שבת *doche
Shabbos*, that's pretty obvious, it isn't דוחה יום טוב *doche Yom Tov*
because if you know you're not gonna cook from יום טוב *Yom
Tov* for שבת *Shabbos*, you know maybe that's debatable if that's מעיקר
הדין *me'ikar hadin* allowed, whole discussion about עירוב תבשילין eruv tavshilin *eiruv
tavshilin* or whatever. But okay, that's for the לחם הפנים *Lechem HaPanim*.
The שתי הלחם shtei halechem *shtei halechem* is particularly interesting, you don't
cook it on יום טוב *Yom Tov* for the יום טוב *Yom
Tov* itself. That is particularly interesting. So the משנה Mishnah *mishnah* doesn't
explain why, it just sort of says it. Okay. And then it
says like this, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר משום רבי שמעון בן
הסגן דוחה את יום טוב ואינו דוחה את יום צום *Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer mishum Rabbi Shimon ben HaSgan doche es haYom Tov
ve'eino doche es Yom Tzom*. Nope, it does override יום טוב *Yom
Tov*, okay, but it does not override יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. So
if you
know what that means is not only by שבועות Shavuos *Shavuos* can
you bake it on יום טוב *Yom Tov* and eat it on
יום טוב *Yom Tov*, but it even means for the לחם הפנים
*Lechem HaPanim* you can bake it if יום טוב *Yom Tov* happened
before שבת *Shabbos*, you can bake it on יום טוב *Yom Tov*
to eat it on a later שבת *Shabbos*. I you know to
eat it on a שבת *Shabbos* like nine days from now, eight
days from now. All right, so but if יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*
falls out on ערב שבת *erev Shabbos*, obviously you can't bake it
on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* to eat it on שבת *Shabbos*. So
you have the first position in the משנה Mishnah *mishnah* that you
can't bake it on שבועות Shavuos? *Shavuos* to eat it on שבועות
Shavuos. *Shavuos*, and then the position here of רבי שמעון בן הסגן
*Rabbi Shimon ben HaSgan* that you can bake it on יום טוב
*Yom Tov* to eat it on שבת *Shabbos*, not even the following
שבת *Shabbos* but a שבת *Shabbos* like you know eight days afterwards.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* does with it. אמר
רבינא *Amar Ravina*, said רבינא *Ravina*, לדברי האומר נדרים ונדבות nedarim u'nedavos
אין קרבין ביום טוב *le'divrei ha'omer nedarim unedavos ein kreivin beYom Tov*,
according to the opinion that says there's a whole debate בית שמאי
בית הלל *Beis Shamai Beis Hillel*, ביתסא *Beisa* whatever, it goes way
back, whether you can bring free-will offerings on יום טוב *Yom Tov*.
And you know the reason to say you could is if I
can שחט *shecht* an animal and eat it at home, why can't
I שחט *shecht* it in the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, sprinkle the
blood on the מזבח mizbeach, *mizbe'ach*, and eat the meat? And I'm
still doing it for the sake of eating. So he says for
the one that says they can't be brought on יום טוב *Yom
Tov*, לא תימא *lo teima*... Don't say look, מדאורייתא m'de'oraisa. you can,
it's food, it's אוכל נפש, ochel nefesh, but the רבנן Rabbanan said
don't do it. Why would they say don't do it? שמא ישהה
shema yishehe because they would say, you know, and then we know
this sometimes like they say you gotta you can't get a haircut
on חול המועד Chol HaMoed so so you don't want to we
want to make sure you get it before יום טוב so you
don't say I'll just wait till חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. So if
we told people, you know, you could bring your נדרים ונדבות on
יום טוב, they would like just they would they would just like
postpone them till יום טוב, and and, you know, and now what
would be the problem of postponing them? So if רש"י Rashi says,
you know, there'd be two problems. Number one is maybe you're over
on בל תאחר, Bal Te'acher, you know, maybe you're postponing it beyond
the time when you're actually obligated to bring it. And number two,
it's like not a nice thing to like, you know, stuff that's
like stuff you have to take care of, do it all on
יום טוב. Yes, it is about food, but it's also about like
fulfilling your obligations and like just piling up all this stuff now
you need to do on יום טוב. So don't say that's the
explanation that it's a דרבנן, d'rabbanan, but דאורייתא d'oraisa you can do
it. Why not? הוא דגזרו hu d'gazru אלא מדאורייתא נמי לא חזי.
ela m'de'oraisa nami lo chazi. The position who says it's not valid
must hold it's not valid even מדאורייתא. How do you know? דהשתא
לחם d'hashta lachem
because why can't you bake the שתי הלחם shtei halechem on יום
טוב, on שבועות Shavuos to eat it on שבועות? Shavuos. You can
cook at home and bake at home, why can't you do it
for the שתי הלחם? shtei halechem, So the answer must be that
when it's being done for a קרבן, korban you can do it,
here's the irony, you can do it if it's really directly for
your eating. But if it is fundamentally for a קרבן, korban even
if in the end you're going to eat it, that's not considered
לכם, lachem, that's considered for God and not לכם lachem and fundamentally
you're not allowed to do that on יום טוב. Okay, so it
must be a principle thing, not a דרבנן d'rabbanan and that's why
you can't bake the שתי הלחם shtei halechem on יום טוב because
fundamentally it's for a קרבן. Korban. Why and how do I know
it's not a דרבנן? d'rabbanan? דשתי הלחם דחובת היום הוא d'shtei halechem
d'chovas hayom hu because שתי הלחם you have to bring on שבועות.
Shavuos So ליתא למימר שמא ישהה, leika l'meimar shema yishehe, no דרבנן
d'rabbanan would be relevant. We don't want you to bring bake your
שתי הלחם on שבועות because we don't want you to postpone. What
postpone? They're only brought on שבועות. וקתני אינו דוחה לא את השבת
ולא את יום טוב. ve'kasani eino doche lo es haShabbos ve'lo es
Yom Tov. Okay, so the משנה Mishnah, makes it clear that you
cannot bake the שתי הלחם to eat them on שבועות and that
proves that if it were דרבנן d'rabbanan that would not be meaningful.
So it proves that that opinion is that even though you're going
to eat it, it's not דאורייתא d'oraisa allowed on יום טוב because
fundamentally it's for the sake of a קרבן Korban even if in
the end you will eat it. And what's particularly interesting is the
position of רבי שמעון השקמוני Rabbi Shimon HaShikuni and again, you know,
this whole idea of עירוב תבשילין is sort of like יום טוב
preparing for שבת, but here he allows יום טוב even to prepare
for the
שבת not only is it a קרבן korban, context, but it's יום
טוב preparing for שבת, but two שבתות Shabbosos from now. All right,
so that is the end of the discussion of שתי הלחם, appropriately
or excuse me, not שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים ve'lechem hapanim but still
appropriately named פרק perek and הדרן עלך שתי הלחם. hadran alach shtei
halechem. Okay so let's just get started now with the next
פרק. perek. המנחות
והנסכים hamenachos ve'hanesachim שנטמאו עד שלא קדשו בכלי shenitme'u ad shelo kidshu
b'kli יש להם פדיון. yesh lahem pidyon. Okay, if you have מנחה
mincha or נסכים, nesachim, you know, the whatever we're talking about, the
flour and the oil or the wine or שנטמאו shenitme'u and they
became טמא. tamei. So עד שלא קדשו בכלי ad shelo kidshu b'kli
before they've even been put into a כלי שרת, Klei Shares, יש
להם פדיון, yesh lahem pidyon, you can redeem them. Okay, they at
this stage they don't have what's called קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf, they
only have קדושת דמים, kedushas damim, their value, until they're put in
a כלי שרת Klei Shares and something that's only קדוש for its
value, the whole you know you can sell that and transfer it.
If I sanctify my car, the goal is now that בית המקדש
sells a car, uses the proceeds, the proceeds become you know the
קדושה kedusha transfers to the proceeds, to the money and they use
that to buy what they want. Okay, so this מנחה נסכים mincha
nesachim before they're in a כלי שרת Klei Shares, they're only קדוש
in terms of their value, it's not considered like an intrinsic קדושה
kedusha and therefore they can be redeemed.
משקדשו בכלי אין להם פדיון. mishekidshu b'kli ein lahem pidyon. Once they
are sanctified in a כלי, kli, then it's קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf
and once something has a קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf it cannot be
redeemed.
העופות והעצים והלבונה וכלי שרת. ha'ofos ve'ha'etzim ve'halevona ve'chlei shares.
Now, birds and wood, wood that you're going to put offer up
on the מזבח, לבונה Levonah frankincense, and actual כלי
שרת kli sharet itself. משנטמאו אין להם פדיון. mishenitme'u ein lahem pidyon.
If they became טמא tamei you cannot redeem them. Why? שלא נאמר
פדיון אלא בבהמה shelo ne'emar pidyon ela b'behema because redeeming was only
said by animals. The תורה Torah says that if an animal has
a מום mum you can redeem it. But it doesn't say by
anything else once it has קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf it doesn't say
that you can redeem it, that is unique by animals. Now, this
is a complicated משנה Mishnah because you know it like... Why are
you singling out, I mean we'll see the answer to this in
the גמרא, Gemara but why are you singling out birds and wood
and לבונה Levonah and כלי שרת? kli sharet. I mean it sounds
like they're in a different category by מנחה ונסכים, Mincha Unesachim, but
the מנחות והנסכים Minchos Vahanesachim were the same point. Once they're sanctified
by a כלי שרת, kli sharet. they cannot be redeemed, even though
they're טמא. Tamei. Whereas animals, right, when they get a מום, Mum,
can be redeemed. So that's like an animal's considered to be already
קדושת הגוף Kedushas Haguf when it's sanctified for a קרבן. korban So
there's a difference right there. You know, also difference of מום Mum
and טמא, Tamei, but nevertheless, you know, there is a difference right
there between מנחה ונסכים Mincha Unesachim versus animals. So what is specifically
here listing עופות, Ofos, עצים, Eitzim, לבונה levona, and כלי שרת? kli
sharet So we'll see this, this'll become clearer when we get to
the גמרא. Gemara Okay, let's start and take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, said שמואל, Shmuel, ואפילו הן טהורים.
Va'afilu Hein Tehorim. When you can first, before we get to that
whole second part of the משנה, Mishnah. let's start with the first
part. You can redeem מנחה ונסכים Mincha Unesachim that become טמא Tamei
before you put it in a כלי שרת. kli sharet. שמואל Shmuel
says, I want you to know that you can do it even
before they become טמא. Tamei. Okay, before they're put in a כלי
שרת, kli sharet. then they're only as I said קדושת דמים. Kedushas
Damim. If it's קדושת דמים, Kedushas Damim, you can just be פודה
Podeh it and, you know, for whatever reason. It's just sanctified, you
know, there's no threshold. You don't need it to be a problem
and it's טמא Tamei and now what am I going to do?
Oh, I'll transfer the money because I can't bring the thing itself.
No, if it only has קדושת דמים, Kedushas Damim, you just can
transfer it. You can be פודה Podeh it straight. Okay, so then
ואפילו הן טהורים נפדים. Va'afilu Hein Tehorim Nifdim. מאי טעמא? Mai Ta'ama?
כל כמה דלא קידשו בכלי, Kol Kama Delo Kidshu Bechli, as long
as you haven't put it in a כלי שרת, kli sharet, קדושת
דמים נינהו. Kedushas Damim Ninhu. It's only a קדושה Kedushah of a
value. וקדושת דמים נפדים, Ukdushat Damim Nifdim, and that you can redeem.
Like I say, if I sanctify my car, you don't need a
criteria till I can, you know, transfer it. The whole idea is
you sell the car and you take the proceeds and it's about
the value of it. You know, what do they say? The cynic
is somebody that knows the cost of everything and the value of
nothing. So anyway, maybe that's the difference between קדושת דמים Kedushas Damim
and קדושת הגוף. Kedushas Haguf. קדושת הגוף Kedushas Haguf is its value,
but קדושת דמים Kedushas Damim if it's its cost. Okay, so until
it's put in a כלי Kli and it gets an identity type
of a קדושה, Kedushah, it's just about the cost, and therefore, you
know, what is it worth? And therefore, that can just be transferred.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא נטמאו תנן. Pshita, Nitmu Tnan.
But the משנה Mishnah says when they're טמא Tamei you can redeem
it. So he says, no, הוא הדין דאף על גב דלא נטמאו,
Hu Hadin De'af Al Gav Delo Nitmu, and this is actually a
pretty good read of the משנה. Mishnah No, you can redeem it
even if they didn't become טמא. Tamei. ואיידי דקבעי למיתני סיפא משיקדשו
בכלי אין להם פדיון, Ve-Aidi Dekaba'i Lemisni Seifa, Misheyikdeshu Bechli Ein Lahem
Pidyon, since the חידוש Chidush is to say once they become sanctified
in a כלי, Kli, you can no longer redeem them. And you
can't redeem them even if it means you have no choice and
you're going to have to destroy it. It became טמא. Tamei. If
you don't let me redeem it, it's טמא, Tamei, I can't use
it. So maybe because of that extreme circumstance you'll let me redeem
it? So the משנה mishna. wants to say sorry, but still no.
Once it was sanctified בכלי, Bechli, you can't redeem it even if
it's טמא, Tamei, even if it means you're going to have to
destroy it. Okay, ואיידי דקבעי למיתני סיפא משיקדשו בכלי אין להם פדיון,
Ve-Aidi Dekaba'i Lemisni Seifa, Misheyikdeshu Bechli Ein Lahem Pidyon, that once it's
sanctified they don't have redemption, דאפילו נטמאו נמי לא, De'afilu Nitmu Nami
Lo, even if they're טמא Tamei once it's in a כלי Kli
it's too late, תנא נמי רישא שנטמאו עד שלא קידשו בכלי. Tana
Nami Reisha Shenitmu Ad Shelo Kidshu Bechli. So therefore the beginning tells
you that it's a scenario of when they become טמא. Tamei. But
if you want to know the actual הלכה, Halacha, before they're in
a כלי, Kli, you can redeem them even if they did not
become טמא. Tamei. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא קדושת
הגוף נינהו. Pshita, Kedushas Haguf Ninhu. So the גמרא Gemara says, but
what's the חידוש Chidush that when they're in a כלי Kli you
can't redeem it? Once they've put in a כלי שרת kli sharet.
you can't redeem it. Meaning, you could have said the חידוש, Chidush,
if you said נטמאו Nitmu in the beginning of the משנה mishna
is a חידוש, Chidush, then it's telling you even before it's a
כלי, Kli, you can't redeem it unless it becomes טמא. Tamei. But
שמואל Shmuel chooses not to read it that way. Before it's a
כלי, Kli, געזונטהייט, Gezuntheit, redeem it whenever you want. The חידוש Chidush
is after a כלי, Kli, even if it's טמא, Tamei, you can't
redeem it. So the גמרא Gemara says, well that's pretty obvious. פשיטא
קדושת הגוף נינהו. Pshita, Kedushas Haguf Ninhu. Once it's in a כלי
שרת, kli sharet that's a קדושה Kedushah of its intrinsic identity, and
therefore, you know, the whole principle of קדושת הגוף Kedushas Haguf is
it can't be redeemed. That is now its identity. So of course
being טמא Tamei would not allow you to redeem it. So the
גמרא Gemara says אצטריך. Itzterich. No, I need it to tell me
this. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka Datach Amina, I would have thought to
say הואיל ובעל מום קרי טמא, Ho'il U-Ba'al Mum Karei Tamei, טמא
נמי כבעל מום דמי. Tamei Nami Keba'al Mum Dami. When an animal
has a מום, Mum, you know, the תורה Torah calls it טמא.
Tamei. We'll see where that gets, you know, what that's based on.
So therefore, meaning by analogy, an animal that you sanctify as a
קרבן has קדושת הגוף, Kedushas Haguf, that's its identity. It's like an
עולה Olah or a שלמים. Shelamim. And nevertheless, you can redeem it
when it has a מום. Mum. So I might think that something
else that has קדושת הגוף, Kedushas Haguf, if it has something analogous
to a מום, Mum, like it's טמא, Tamei, maybe you can redeem
that as well. If you're also allowed to redeem it. That actually
is a good analogy. Okay, ואף על גב דקדוש קדושת הגוף, Ve'af
al gav dekadosh kedushat haguf, and even though, but an animal, even
though it has קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, כי נפל ביה מום מפרק,
ki nafal bei mum mifrak, once it has a מום mum you
can redeem it. הני נמי ליפרק. Hani nami lifrak. So if the
Torah lets me redeem an animal with a מום mum even though
it has קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, it could allow me to redeem,
you know, מנחה mincha and נסכים that are with קדושת הגוף kedushat
haguf that became טמא tamei once they become unusable. קמשמע לן דלאו
כי האי טמא קרי רחמנא לבעל מום. Kamashma lan delav ke'hai tamei
kari Rachmana leba'al mum.
No, the Torah when it calls a בעל מום ba'al mum טמא,
tamei, it does not mean to abstract it and apply this principle
to other, to general cases of טומאה. tumah. This is a special
allowance for a בעל מום ba'al mum of an animal that does
not apply to other things. And by the way, you know, that
fits very well with the end of the mishna. Okay. שאין פדיון
נאמר אלא בבהמה. She'ein pidyon ne'emar ella bevehema.
So if you take out these weird cases in the middle of
the mishna, עופות עצים לבונה וכלי שרת, ofot etzim levona uchlei sharet,
the beginning and the end of the mishna read nicely together. A
מנחה mincha that becomes טמא tamei you can't redeem, a מנחה mincha
that's put in a כלי שרת kli sharet, and has קדושת הגוף
kedushat haguf you can't, even if it becomes טמא tamei you can't
redeem because the idea of redeeming something that with קדושת הגוף kedushat
haguf that can't be used was only said in the context of
a בהמה behema with a מום. mum. All right, so putting those
two in contrast works very nicely. Let's just read a little bit
more before we end for today. Okay. דמכלי שרת לא אשכחן דמיפרק.
Dimekli sharet lo ashchan demifrak. Okay,
because we have never found anything that can be redeemed after it's
been sanctified with a כלי שרת. kli sharet. An animal has קדושת
הגוף, kedushat haguf, it's interesting, but even before it's sanctified with a
כלי kli. שרת. When you שחט it with a knife, that's an
additional sanctification of a כלי kli שרת and then you can't redeem
the animal. So what the גמרא never explains is why does an
animal as soon as you say the words you're sanctifying it, why
does that give it its identity and it's considered קדושת הגוף, kedushat
haguf, but when you sanctify flour for a מנחה, it doesn't have
its identity and it's not קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf until it's put
in a כלי שרת. The גמרא never, you know, really, you know,
explain explains why that is. It's something of a sense that an
animal is an עולה olah or a שלמים, shelamim, you know, even
as it's still alive, even if it's still an animal, where a
מנחה isn't a מנחה until it's like brought to the בית המקדש
and put in a כלי. But that's more a little circular. I
still haven't really explained why by the מנחה the כלי is קדושת
הגוף kedushat haguf and the animal it's automatic. That the גמרא just
takes for granted. So it says by an animal the Torah lets
you redeem it because even though it has קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf,
okay, it hasn't been put in a כלי שרת. But once something
gets its קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf by being put in a כלי
שרת, no redemption. And now just to finish the thought: ובעל מום
היכא איקרי טמא? Uba'al mum heicha ikri tamei? Where is a בעל
מום ba'al mum called טמא? tamei? דתניא, Detanya, we learn in a
ברייתא: ואם כל בהמה טמאה, Ve'im kol behema tmeia, because the very
פסוק pasuk that speaks about redeeming a בעל מום ba'al mum uses
the word טמא. tamei. And here's what the פסוק pasuk says: ואם
כל בהמה טמאה אשר לא יקריבו ממנה קרבן לה׳. Ve'im kol behema
tmeia asher lo yakrivu mimena korban l'Hashem. You know, and if you
sanctified something that is impure that's not a קרבן, then it says
you can redeem it.
בבעלי מומין שהכתוב מדבר. Bevalei mumin shehakatuv medaber. So this when it
says טמא, tamei, it doesn't literally mean טמא. tamei. It means a
בעל מום. ba'al mum. אתה אומר בבעלי מומין שהכתוב מדבר או אינו
אלא בבהמה טמאה ממש? Atah omer bevalei mumin shehakatuv medaber o eino
ella bevehema tmeia mamash? You're saying it's talking about a בעל מום
ba'al mum that you are
redeeming, or maybe it means try to sanctify like, you know, a
camel or
something? No, כשהוא אומר ואם בבהמה הטמאה ופדה בערכך. Keshehu omer ve'im
babehema hatmeia ufada be'erkecha. No, because another פסוק pasuk in that context
says if it's a בהמה טמאה. behema tmeia. Okay, and then you
redeem it. And that doesn't and that's just straight, simple. הרי בהמה
טמאה אמורה הא מה אני מקיים ואם כל בהמה טמאה בבעלי מומין
שהכתוב מדבר. Harei behema tmeia amura ha mah ani mekayem ve'im kol
behema tmeia bevalei mumin shehakatuv medaber. That's already the case, בהמה טמאה.
behema tmeia. So why is it saying another case of
בהמה טמאה? behema tmeia? It's talking about an animal with a blemish.
Now some try to, you know, emphasize that that really is פשט
pshat because it says אשר לא יקריבו ממנה קרבן לה׳, asher lo
yakrivu mimena korban l'Hashem, right? So if it's a camel you don't
have to say אשר לא יקריבו ממנה קרבן לה׳. asher lo yakrivu
mimena korban l'Hashem. So what it means is an animal that is
of a species that you normally could, but now it is טמא
tamei in a way that you cannot bring this particular animal. So
what does that mean? So what we mean by טמא tamei is
we mean blemished, okay? But the אשר לא יקריב asher lo yakriv
is like sort more like an accidental quality to it, right? It
could have just said בהמה טמאה. behema tmeia. So that's how we
understand it means a בעל מום. ba'al mum. יכול יפדה המום עובר?
Yachol yifdeh hamum over? Maybe you can even do it even if
it's a blemish that will heal? תלמוד לומר אשר לא יקריבו ממנה
קרבן לה׳. Talmud lomar asher lo yakrivu mimena korban l'Hashem. That you
will not be able to bring a קרבן of God from it.
מי שאינה קריבה לה׳ כל עיקר יצאה זו Mi she'eina kreiva l'Hashem
kol ikar yatza'ah zu שאינה קריבה היום וקריבה למחר, she'eina kreiva hayom
ukreiva lemachar, okay, that cannot be brought today but can be brought
tomorrow, so that is not absolutely not able to be brought. So
what we've established now is That a בהמה behema is considered קדושת
הגוף kedushat haguf and can be redeemed even with a מום. mum.
It's קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf from the moment you sanctify it. מנחה
נסכים, everything that's not a בהמה, behema, it only gets קדושת הגוף
kedushat haguf when you put it in a כלי שרת. Okay, once
you put it in a כלי שרת and it gets קדושת הגוף,
kedushat haguf, it cannot be redeemed. בהמה behema with a מום, mum,
yes, something that was put in a כלי שרת, no. Alright, and
it's only an allowance by בהמה behema and that nicely explains the
contrast of בהמה behema to the beginning of the משנה. What we're
going to get to tomorrow is parsing this middle of the משנה
of why it's singling out עופות, ofot, עצים, etzim, לבונה, and כלי
שרת. Okay, we will end here for now.